<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a friend with remarks upon two pamphlets lately published, in defence of tritheism viz. A brief enquiry by J. T. and The Socinian slain by J.H.</title>
            <author>A. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13174601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13174601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98347</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27348)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98347)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 445:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a friend with remarks upon two pamphlets lately published, in defence of tritheism viz. A brief enquiry by J. T. and The Socinian slain by J.H.</title>
                  <author>A. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: A. B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>J. H. --  Socinian slain.</term>
               <term>Taylor, Joseph, 17th/18th cent. --  Brief inquiry whether they who assert ... the divinity of our Lord Jesus, may have communion together.</term>
               <term>Monotheism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tritheism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98347:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend: WITH REMARKS Upon two Pamphlets, lately publiſhed, In Defence of TRITHEISM; <hi>VIZ.</hi> A BRIEF ENQUIRY. By <hi>J. T.</hi> And THE SOCINIAN SLAIN. By <hi>J. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>In malâ cauſâ non poſſunt aliter, at cauſam</l>
               <l>Malam quis coégit eos habere!</l> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed, <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> M.DCC.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98347:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98347:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have, at your requeſt, read over two little Books you were pleas'd to put into my hands; <hi>viz. The Brief Enquiry,</hi> which I find was written by <hi>J. T.</hi> and, <hi>The Socinian Slain,</hi> written, as 'tis reported, by one <hi>J. H.</hi> And really, Sir, when I have perus'd ſuch Diſcourſes, written with an Air of Candour and Sincerity; and when I ſee the Authors ſo very zealous in defending their own Miſtakes, and find them loading with heavy Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations the Opinions of others, I cannot but extreamly regret the ill uſage of thoſe important Truths they undertake to confute: and I aſſure you am at the ſame time no leſs concern'd that ſo much Zeal, as theſe two Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have expreſs'd, ſhould be miſpent in a wrong Cauſe; and not barely ſo, but in oppoſition to the moſt <hi>Natural</hi> and moſt <hi>Scriptural Notion</hi> that the <hi>beſt of Men,</hi> and the <hi>beſt of Chriſtians</hi> have ever had of the <hi>Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How unhappily have theſe Men, and a great many others who have earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended in theſe Controverſies, in concluſion prov'd nothing ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as this, That Education and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt are irreſiſtable; that they will put ſuch a biaſs upon a wiſe Man's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and manner of reaſoning, which without extraordinary Care and divine Aſſiſtance, will become almoſt inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to him.</p>
            <p>I ſay almoſt, and not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable; becauſe I'm perſwaded there is no Man ſo much under the power of Miſtake in the common neceſſary Points of Religion, but may be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, if he makes his Enquiries with any tolerable degree of Candour and Ingenuity.</p>
            <p>But when a man ſets up for abſolute Certainty in a controverted Point, and ſpeaks and dictates like an inſpired Writer, there remains no remedy for his Errors, till he is cur'd of his Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility.</p>
            <p>What opinion theſe two Perſons have of their own Performances, is certainly known to God and their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences alone: but they give abundant ſatisfaction to the World, that they are Men who have not temper enough for any Contronverſy, nor skill enough to manage this.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The late Bp of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Bp <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> Bp <hi>Sarum,</hi> Bp <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>How.</hi>
               </note>The moſt eminent Writers both for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Dignity, have written againſt us with the Decency of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the Temper of good Chriſtians; they make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that they can be candid and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to an Adverſary; and how warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoever they are engag'd in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, yet they keep within the bounds of Religion and good Breeding. And tho the Cauſe they engaged in was never to be confuted, yet 'tis own'd, if it could have been, they certainly had done it. But this <hi>Brace of Writers</hi> have taken up the Diſpute, when the field was quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the moſt <hi>ſober</hi> and moſt <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> of our Opponents: and when the moſt celebrated Univerſity of <hi>Oxon</hi> had decreed in our favour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd the vulgar <hi>Tritheiſtic Trinity,</hi> and the Rev. Dean of <hi>Paul</hi>'s had in his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98347:3"/>
               <hi>State of the Socinian Controverſy,</hi> with a Modeſty that became a Man of his Dignity and Learning, handſomely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, or at leaſt prudently ſoften'd whatever had the countenance and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> in his former Writings.</p>
            <p>With what good Grace then can theſe two Writers of the loweſt Claſs, who, it may be, were never taught in any Claſs, undertake to revive the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate that was given over by the beſt and wiſeſt Gentlemen of the <hi>Tritheiſtic Party?</hi> Do they think they can ſay ſomewhat better than any that have written before them? ſure they are too modeſt to be of that opinion: or is it becauſe they will ſay and argue as no body would beſides them? this may be true enough indeed: for they both of them argue and prove in that unuſual Method that one may ſee at the firſt bluſh, that they <hi>underſtand not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They knew (certainly) when they began to write, that this Controverſy, whatever others might be, was <hi>terra incognita</hi> to 'em both; and yet, which is very much to be admir'd, they are as <hi>poſitive</hi> and as <hi>decretory</hi> as if they acted by <hi>Legantine Authority</hi> from the <hi>Holy See,</hi> and came not to <hi>debate,</hi> but <hi>decide</hi> this controverted Point.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Brief Enquiry, Pref.</hi> tells his Readers with very great gravity— Gentlemen, pray take notice, <hi>I write only for Truth;</hi> but I remember the time when he durſt not diſpute for it, and made an honeſt and true confeſſion that he could not.</p>
            <p>And he adds, <hi>(ibid.) That Chriſtian Charity muſt not be abus'd towards thoſe who root up the Foundations of Religion:</hi> no, nor muſt it be abus'd towards any Perſons whatever, nor on any account whatever. To abuſe Chriſtian Charity would be a great abuſe indeed; but to abuſe it for the ſake of ill Men, would ſtill be a much greater abuſe. But I ſuppoſe he would inſinuate that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> root up the Foundations of Religion, and that to treat 'em chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably, would be to abuſe Chriſtian Charity, which ought not to be done. God forgive him for his uncharitable Inſinuation, and we will too; but let him remember there is not a more ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy abuſe of the Chriſtian, nor of any Religion indeed, than to affirm that it teaches us not to exerciſe Charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men of a different Opinion.</p>
            <p>But tho the <hi>Brief Enquirer</hi> be ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wary how he abuſes Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; yet, to the great ſcandal of all pious Chriſtians, he cares not what abuſes he flings at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion,</hi> provided he can expoſe the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians:</hi> for, abating a few pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, a good part of his Book conſiſts in odious Compariſons of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> with <hi>Mahometaniſm,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>Mahomet:</hi> and if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be not the <hi>Supreme God,</hi> and of the ſame <hi>Eſſence</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi> he wickedly infers, to the juſt abhorrence of all that love the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> in truth and ſincerity, <hi>P.</hi> 14 and 51. <hi>That Chriſt was an Impoſtor and Deceiver; that the Jews juſtly ſentenc'd him to death for Blaſphemy, and rejected his Apoſtles; that the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Idolatry and Superſtition, and the Meſſiah is not yet come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And theſe terrible Inferences are not made <hi>en paſſant,</hi> and by the by; but he continues to copy Monſieur <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badie</hi>'s rude, ſcandalous, and impious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98347:3"/>Expreſſions for ſeveral pages together.</p>
            <p>If, ſays he, <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is not true God, of the ſame Eſſence with the Father, the Mahometan Religion is preferable to the Chriſtian, and</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet <hi>a greater Prophet than</hi> Chriſt, <hi>becauſe the Chriſtian Religion brings in Idolatry, and the Mahometan aboliſhes it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How gladly would the <hi>Brief Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> prove the Mahometan to be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Religion! why elſe dos he take that for granted to prove it, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body denys; <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion</hi> brings in <hi>Idolatry:</hi> for there is no Chriſtian, but the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Enquirer,</hi> and his <hi>Abbadie,</hi> who inſinuates a Charge of <hi>Idolatry</hi> againſt the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> upon account of the Honour therein given to Chriſt. Even thoſe <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who are for a <hi>co-equal Adoration</hi> of three <hi>co-equal co-eternal Beings,</hi> abhor the charging Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry upon the <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> much leſs will they, or can they be thought to countenance ſo deteſtable an Accuſation, who declare for the ſupreme Honour and Adoration of <hi>one ſingle Infinite All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Being,</hi> who is the <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He proceeds in his <hi>deteſtable Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and aſſerts, <hi>p.</hi> 16. That <hi>the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Jeſus Chriſt is Idolatry, if he is not God.</hi> How! dares the <hi>Enquirer</hi> aſſert, that to honour him whom <hi>God the Father</hi> has honour'd (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.) and highly exalted, is <hi>Idolatry</hi> that to give him a Name above every Name, and confeſs him <hi>Lord,</hi> to the <hi>Glory of God the Father,</hi> is <hi>Idolatry? Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. ſee <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.22, 23. What No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I wonder has this <hi>haſty Enquirer</hi> of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and of <hi>Idolatry!</hi> I dare be his Security that he is a perfect Stranger to the true Notion of either of 'em, how loudly ſoever he may declaim with the dreadful Charge of <hi>Idolatry:</hi> for I would demand of this <hi>bold Enquirer,</hi> where is the Idolatry? if the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> have all the honour and venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paid him, but that alone which he himſelf gave to <hi>his Father</hi> and our <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and to <hi>his God</hi> and <hi>our God,</hi> to whom he aſcended. Yet this <hi>Bold En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirer, p.</hi> 16. takes a freſh ſtart from this very Charge, too too like a good <hi>Muſſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> to extol his <hi>holy Prophet Mahomet</hi> for a very conſiderable Teacher, and a great Reformer of Mankind. How deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Caſe is it, that ſome Men write juſt as they have liv'd, like true Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans; and have preſented the World with a fair occaſion to conclude they would be extreamly gratify'd if their <hi>Arabian Prophet's</hi> Religion were eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd in <hi>England:</hi> for a good <hi>Muſſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> may keep a <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> and a <hi>brace of Concubines</hi> at the ſame time: <hi>for they are not incommunicable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Enquirer, p.</hi> 16. to ſhew you his good liking of <hi>Mahomet</hi> and his Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, inſiſts upon it in a large Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Encomium on both; <hi>How can we but have a great opinion of</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet <hi>He hath taught Men ſo and ſo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>What can beſpeak a Man more inſpired of God? Surely he was a very great Prophet, and all he hath taught ought to be own'd as Divine.</hi> P. 17, 18. <hi>He is a greater Prophet than all under the Law, yea preferable to Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which,</hi> ſays he, <hi>p.</hi> 19. <hi>will appear if you conſider his Doctrine, or the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his Miniſtry—He hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd his Religion upon firm Foundations, and taken wiſer Methods—, and was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98347:4"/>much wiſer and better than Chriſt; he had greater Candour, Truth and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, greater care of, and zeal for the Glory of God than Jeſus Chriſt, who makes himſelf one with the moſt High God.</hi> P. 21. <hi>If Chriſt was not God,</hi> Mahomet <hi>ſpoke more truly and plainly than Chriſt, had more Wiſdom, and took more care not to entangle the Souls of Men.</hi> P. 22. <hi>Nay if Chriſt was not true God, he was an Impoſtor, and his Diſciples Deceivers, and the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion is a Cheat, Superſtition and Idolatry.</hi> What a terrible Outrage is here upon the Chriſtian Religion! Theſe are the execrable Conſequences the confident Enquirer preſumes to draw from his obſcure, equivocal and unexpounded Premiſes, and has taken a ſcandalous liberty of publiſhing this Raillery upon the Chriſtian Religion in a Chiſtian Nation, and with his own name in the Title Page: Are theſe the Fruits of his Zeal and his Orthodoxy? Muſt Chriſtianity it ſelf be decry'd and vilify'd, if it be not the thing he miſtakes it to be? Is this the rare Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of confuting the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians?</hi> this will rather ſerve to confirm 'em in this Truth, That they and the Chriſtian Religion muſt ſtand and fall together; and he that deſigns to confute them and what they maintain, does in effect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake nothing leſs than a Confutation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Divine Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What this <hi>Enquirer</hi> is maintaining in the remainder of his Book is a full and complete inſtance of <hi>this:</hi> for <hi>he</hi> produces Text upon Text, and one Scripture upon another, to ſhew that <hi>another diſtinct Being is a moſt High God,</hi> beſide him <hi>who is the God and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and unleſs you will grant him this Senſe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this Proof to be ſufficient, he'll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the H. Scriptures, and give the prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his <hi>beloved Alchoran:</hi> for that teaches, as he informs you, That <hi>none other but the eternal Father is God, p.</hi> 21. whereas he looks upon it as certain and evident, that Jeſus Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles taught, that another, nay a third diſtinct Being, are truly and properly <hi>Gods, coequal in Nature and Perfection,</hi> and have equal right to Divine Honour and Adoration. P. 24, 25, 26. <q>That Jeſus Chriſt is God in the higheſt and chiefeſt ſenſe, he begins to prove from the Names, the incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Names of God aſcribed to him.</q> Yet Jeſus Chriſt no where once ſtiles himſelf God, or aſcribes to himſelf the nature of God; and God has no incommunicable Name, that I could ever meet with; no Name but what is given to other Beings beſides himſelf. If the giving the Names of God to any Being beſides him, be Blaſphemy; <hi>J. T.</hi> I doubt will renounce his <hi>Bible</hi> as well as <hi>Christ,</hi> and embrace the Doctrine of the <hi>Alchoran,</hi> which ſome affirm beſt ſuits with his Life and good Opinion. He finds in his Bible the Names of God given to Angels, good and evil, to Princes and Prophets: nay he himſelf takes all the pains he can, to prove that the Names, the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable Names of God are given to Jeſus Chriſt. Now if the Man Chriſt Jeſus be not God, then Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> has prov'd that the Names of God are not incommunicable, for he proves that they are given to Chriſt: ſo that it muſt follow, either that the Names may be given to different Beings in a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98347:4"/>different Senſe, or that God and Jeſus Chriſt are but one Being, or that the Scripture-phraſes are miſapplied, which it may be he will rather incline to believe.</p>
            <p>But he goes on to inform you, <hi>p.</hi> 25. That <hi>Jehovah is a Name only belongs to the moſt High God.</hi> Pſal. 83.18. <hi>Thou whoſe Name alone is Jehovah.</hi> This is a very pleaſant Proof: for if there be another Perſon or Being beſides the Father, of whom it may be ſaid, <hi>Thou whoſe Name is Jehovah,</hi> then the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's</hi> Name alone is not <hi>Jehovah;</hi> for <hi>J. T.</hi> ſays it belongs to another Perſon or Being, who is a Son, and not a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo that this proof deſtroys it ſelf; for if the Father's Name alone be <hi>Jehovah,</hi> ſo as that Name is not to be given to any other beſides him, then Jeſus Chriſt who is another Perſon or Being beſides him, has not and cannot have that Name given or aſcribed to him: but if Jeſus Chriſt has that name given or aſcrib'd to him, which is alſo given to his Father another diſtinct Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then the Pſalmiſt muſt be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſaying of the Father, <hi>Thou whoſe Name alone is Jehovah,</hi> and the Name is no proper Name for one Being, but is only a proper Name in that Senſe that the name <hi>[John]</hi> is, which belonged <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelist,</hi> and ſtill belongs to divers par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 26, 27. The <hi>Enquirer</hi> proceeds from ſeveral divine Perfections to prove, <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt was truly God from eternity:</hi> how well he has done this, is not worth while to examine; others having done it to good purpoſe, and I may conſider 'em elſewhere; tho it may be truly ſaid of his Proofs in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that they prove <hi>one God too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> for the Chriſtian Religion, if they prove Jeſus Chriſt to be a moſt High God from Eternity: for if Jeſus Chriſt was truly ſo from Eternity, that Jeſus Chriſt who was ſo, was not that <hi>very God</hi> who was his <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Fountain</hi> and <hi>Origin</hi> of his Being; but an <hi>eternal God, derived, originated</hi> and <hi>begotten</hi> by another <hi>eternal God</hi> even the <hi>Father,</hi> who is an <hi>underiv'd, origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated</hi> and <hi>unbegotten God;</hi> and ſo even in the <hi>Nicene,</hi> nay in the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Senſe, God the Father was the firſt, the Supreme, and the moſt Divine Being or Perſon in the vulgar Senſe. And in this all the Books that have been or can be publiſh'd on this Subject, muſt of neceſſity center at laſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That Jeſus Chriſt, one diſtinct individual Being or Perſon, is an eternal God, becauſe the Deſcriptions and Characters of another divine Perſon, to wit, the Father, who is on all hands granted to be an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God, are, as ſome ſuppoſe, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently given to him: ſo that rather than they will admit Words and Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to have a different Senſe according to the different Objects whereof they are ſpoken, they chooſe to lay down Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that neceſſarily and unavoidably infer, that there are two or three coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and coequal Beings, or Perſons of the ſame <hi>ſort</hi> or <hi>kind</hi> of Divinity. And as the <hi>Enquirer</hi> ſays in another Caſe, <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>We may as ſoon deny the light at Noon-day, as the clearneſs of this Evidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this he proceeds to cite Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by wholeſale, and to interpret Texts in that manner, as if he were reſolv'd to fulfil thoſe words of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. which the ignorant and unſtable wreſt, as they do the reſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98347:5"/>of the Scriptures, to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>How bold he makes with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> is almoſt a ſcandal to relate: for he proves St. <hi>Paul</hi> to contradict the Prophet in expreſs terms: <hi>P.</hi> 32. <q>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſays he, knew that <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had aſſerted there was none to be likened or compar'd to him, <hi>i. e.</hi> to God, and yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> with the greateſt aſſurance aſſerts, that Jeſus Chriſt was in the form of God, and was equal to him. <hi>i. e.</hi>
               </q> What <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expreſly denys, St. <hi>Paul</hi> as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly affirms, that there was one who might be compared to God, becauſe he was abſolutely equal to God; that is in plain Engliſh, there are two coequal Gods, really diſtinct Beings, but of equal and like Perfections.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Enquirer</hi> had neither Skill nor Judgment to examine the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Texts he has cited; but thinks to gain the point by a Poll, he has preſs'd all the Texts he could meet with into his Service, and hopes, I ſuppoſe, that ſome amongſt the crowd will paſs for good Teſtimony; and ſo they do in the opinion of the Crowd: But for the <hi>Trinitarian</hi> Gentlemen that are Men of Learning and Reading, they have with great candour and ſincerity acknowledged, that moſt, if not all the Texts produced by this unſtudied Preacher, are no good Proofs of the matter for which they are alledg'd; ſome I am certain are as much to the purpoſe as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Dreams, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd <hi>Ecce duos gladios:</hi> And I don't ſee but <hi>ecce duos gladios</hi> is as good, and Catholick Proof for two diſtinct Gods, as it paſſes for in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for two diſtinct Juriſdictions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 46. <q>But the <hi>Enquirer</hi> will have the Diſciples of Chriſt to be the worſt of Men, for applying Texts which ſpeak of God in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament to Jeſus Chriſt in the New, if he was not of the ſame Eſſence with the Father.</q> God forbid it!</p>
            <p>But does he not impoſe upon himſelf and his Readers, by the terms <hi>[ſame Eſſence]</hi> for they may ſignify either <hi>one Being,</hi> or <hi>one kind of Being:</hi> if the former, then Jeſus Chriſt will be the Father, and his own Father: if the latter, then <hi>the Father</hi> is <hi>one moſt High Being,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> another of the <hi>ſame kind,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt a Third,</hi> and ſo we ſhall have three diſtinct moſt High Gods.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Enquirer</hi> in <hi>p.</hi> 48, 49. falls upon the odious Proof of Jeſus Chriſt being guilty of Blaſphemy, and fixes the <hi>Jewiſh Calumny</hi> in the ſtricteſt Senſe upon him, <hi>That he made himſelf equal with God, i. e.</hi> that he made himſelf another God; for equality neceſſarily requires two at leaſt: or that Jeſus Chriſt made himſelf equal to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whom the Jews, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s our bleſſed Saviour aſſures us, look'd upon to be the only true God, <hi>John</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. How ready is the <hi>Enquirer</hi> to join hands with the Jews in an unjuſt Accuſation againſt our B. Saviour! for he tells you, <hi>p.</hi> 49. <q>Theſe are the things they alledg in their defence for crucifying Jeſus Chriſt; and we demand, ſays the <hi>Enquirer,</hi> how any Man or Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Men, that deny his Divinity, can take off the force of 'em.</q> So that <hi>J. T.</hi> has made good the Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt Chriſt, and by an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and wicked way of reaſoning, he will put a Dilemma upon his Saviour,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98347:5"/>and, prove him and <hi>God,</hi> as Dr. <hi>A—x</hi> ſomewhere ſtiles him; or guilty of Blaſphemy; for which the <hi>Jews</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly condemn'd him.</p>
            <p>In <hi>P.</hi> 52 and 53. he launches out into a new Subject, and tells you, <hi>The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Euchariſt repreſent Jeſus Chriſt to the Trinitarians giving up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Sacrifice and Satisfaction to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Juſtice;</hi> but to the Socinians as a meer example of patience and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>i. e.</hi> the Elements repreſent God the eternal Son offering himſelf to God the eternal Father, to ſatisfy the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Juſtice; the Son having none it ſeems to ſatisfy. How ſtrange a Repreſentation is this of Chriſt's Death and Sufferings! yet a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar one with the Solifidians.</p>
            <p>Let me deſire the Gentlemen who are Favourers of his Book, to reflect a little upon the Character and Quality of this pious and zealous Defender of Tritheiſm, and I'm much miſtaken if they don't acknowledg that ſo laſcivious a Vindicator is a very improper Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion for their beloved Tritheiſm, that admirable and wonderful Myſtery.</p>
            <p>For if the Unitarians are attack'd, and their Doctrines exploded by Men of ſuch a profligate Life, and flagitious Crimes, as the <hi>Brief Enquirer</hi> has led and committed in the face of the World; they will have very little reaſon to fear their cauſe, tho both Unitarians and Tritheiſts too have great cauſe to be aſham'd of ſuch a ſcandalous Author, whom in his 55th Page you'll find very buſy a proving the poor <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> Hereticks, and their Doctrine He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, and thinks no doubt he has prov'd the point as fully as bis own People prov'd him an Adulterer, and his Grimes Adultery. I ſhould be ſorry I confeſs if the former were as true as the latter, but ſhould have been very glad for <hi>J. T</hi>'s ſake if the latter were no truer than the former. But I would feign know of the <hi>Enquirer</hi> and all his Abettors, which is the greater Hereſy, to aſſert as the Tritheiſts do, That there are three eternal, moſt perfect, coequal Beings; or to maintain, as the Unitarians do, that there is and can be but one ſupreme moſt perfect Being, who has no equal, and with whom no other Being is to be compar'd. If I muſt be an Heretick, for my part I would chooſe for my opinion the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of theſe two Hereſies.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Enquirer</hi> is clearly for the firſt; yet he owns, <hi>P.</hi> 59. <hi>There are few who are capable of underſtanding ſo great a Myſtery:</hi> So ſay the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Defenders of the <hi>Myſtery,</hi> both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Foreigners.</hi> But the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians ſay, and can prove, as they have often done, that 'tis a Myſtery of <hi>Human Invention,</hi> and not of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation;</hi> and by the way, 'tis ſuch a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> that the <hi>Enquirer,</hi> one of the meaneſt of its Defenders, could not ſay one wiſe word in vindication of it at a publick Diſpute: And how could he help it, the <hi>Myſtery</hi> being incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible?</p>
            <p>But he aſſures you, <hi>P.</hi> 69. that <hi>The common People firmly believe the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, tho they can't comprehend the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it.</hi> I anſwer. The Faith of the common People is a groſs <hi>Tritheiſtic</hi> Faith, like that of the <hi>common Preachers,</hi> of which no wiſe Man, nor thinking Chriſtian, can be very fond. I'm ſure the Learned Dr. <hi>S</hi>—<hi>th,</hi> and the moſt Celebrated Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98347:6"/>no value for it, but have ſolemnly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd it, <hi>Nov.</hi> 25. 1695.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Enquirer</hi> has now done with his Proofs, and begins his Remarks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Unitarians, who are ſaid to be, P. 60 <hi>Men of holy and pious Lives,</hi> &amp;c which many. Trinitarians are not, the <hi>Enquirer,</hi> for one; and therefore is ſo ready to ingage St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Hereſy in the Faith, more than Impiety in the Morals. How gladly would ſome Men have their pretended Orthodoxy atone for their real Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality, and be accounted good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians for a <hi>myſterious Faith</hi> without <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>good Life!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Enquirer</hi> admits the Unitarians to be Men of pious lives; but what then, Will that alone qualify 'em for Church-Communion? No by no means, <hi>P.</hi> 62. <hi>If after all means uſed they perſiſt in their Hereſies, they are to he rejected: let their Lives and Converſations be never ſo exact, they are be to rejected by the Church; which ſhews they are not good Chriſtians, and that their Piety is but ſeeming, not real.</hi> Let me recommend for once to all and ſingular of his Reader or Readers, this elaborate <hi>Lipotiwhichet</hi> as one of his Maſterpieces; and I challenge 'em to match it in all the Sayings of all the <hi>Seven Wiſe Maſters in Chriſtendom, Bevis of Southampton, Criſpin,</hi> or King <hi>Pharamond:</hi> For I'm ſure that this is true Mother-Wit, and a perfect Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of his own Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>But what if one ſhould argue, The <hi>Enquirer</hi> is really immoral, and but ſeemingly Orthodox, therefore he ought to be caſt out of the Church; Would not this look with a far better Grace than his Argument? <hi>viz.</hi> You ought to be caſt out of the Church, <hi>ergo,</hi> you are but ſeemingly pious and good Chriſtians. No, no, the <hi>Enquirer</hi> will reply, By no means <hi>[You ought to be caſt out of the Church]</hi> is a ſtanch Reaſon at all times to prove <hi>Hereſy</hi> and <hi>Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and when all other Arguments fail, this will do: for whoever ought to be caſt out of the Church, can neither be a good Man, nor a true Chriſtian. The <hi>Enquirer</hi> and all his Friends are agreed that the Unitarians ought to be caſt out of the Church; and then to be ſure they are no good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But what if the Unitarians ſhould think the <hi>Enquirer</hi> ought to be caſt out of the Church, Would not this prove him no <hi>Chriſtian</hi> too? Yes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if his own Argument be a good one: but his Congregation I hear have done him that piece of Juſtice already, and the zealous Excluder is himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and declar'd in his own Stile, <hi>Incommunicable:</hi> which ſeems to be a remarkable inſtance of Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon him, for vilifying his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, reproaching his Saviour, extolling <hi>Mahomet,</hi> decrying the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> which is the beſt <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians the trueſt Profeſſors of it.</hi> He who wrote to encourage Schiſm, and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, has his own Church firſt broken and divided, and then himſelf upon full evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſentenc'd, and declared incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable by that very dividing Party, who were his unwary Admirers. <hi>How righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous are thy Judgments, O God!</hi> Pſal. 73.25. <hi>Whom have we in Heaven but Thee? and whom is there on Earth that we ought to eſteem or adore in compariſon with thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God grant him repentance unto life: he is at preſent in the gall of bitterneſs and bond of Iniquity; for that reaſon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98347:6"/>under the Church's righteous <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma;</hi> his pretended Orthodoxy could not reſcue him from the Cenſure: and without a ſolemn Renunciation of his former Life, of whatever ſtamp his religious Opinions are, he muſt unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably fall under the <hi>Maranatha</hi> of an affronted Deity.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I think without a Spirit of Prophecy, I may foretel the <hi>unrepenting Enquirer's</hi> Doom: but I am yet to tell you the Fate both of the Arguments, and the Author of the <hi>Socinian Slain, P.</hi> 1. who talks ſo much of his Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, that I am tempted to think him rather a Maſter of the noble Science of Defence, than a Maſter of Arts. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever and whatever this Writer is, I wiſh he had been inſpir'd with a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Meekneſs and Humility, before he had undertaken this Task, and then we had met with more Charity and Modeſty in his Diſcourſe: and I hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſh he had taken the Spirit of Truth for his Guide, and then he had made a better uſe of the Sword of the Spirit, than he has now done with the Arm of Fleſh.</p>
            <p>But alas for him, he knows not what Spirit he is of, tho his Readers may eaſily ſee that he has a Spirit of Envy and Uncharitableneſs; and that he has not the Civility of a Gentleman, or the Temper of a Chriſtian, by his ill Language, and abuſive Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the <hi>2d,</hi> 38th, 48th, <hi>52d, 53d</hi> pages.</p>
            <p>But the Unitarians muſt be decry'd at any rate, and ſo that be done, it matters not what the Arguments are. He would not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouble himſelf to ſtand to pick and chooſe; or if he did make a choice, he has taken the moſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive and the moſt ill-natur'd he could light upon.</p>
            <p>Socin. Slain, p. 2. <hi>When</hi> (ſays the Socinian Slain) <hi>a Neighbour's Houſe is on Fire, or the Air infected with the Peſtilence, and the Enemies of God and his Servants are in a Combination, and lie in wait to deceive the Ignorant and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>wary, it's every Man's Duty to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the Flame,</hi> &amp;c. This is very true; and the Unitarians have a good Title to theſe Conſiderations: But what has any <hi>Athanaſian</hi> or <hi>Tritheiſtic Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to do with 'em? The <hi>Fire,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence,</hi> and <hi>Craft</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> have done too too much Injury to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith</hi> already; and has deceiv'd this very <hi>unwary Writer,</hi> and all <hi>his Elect,</hi> if any one can truly be ſaid to be deceiv'd by another, who impoſes upon himſelf by ſuch <hi>inconſiderable So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry,</hi> as runs through bis whole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>He firſt takes it for granted, that by the Holy Ghoſt we are to underſtand a ſingle intelligent Being or Subſiſtence, diſtinct from the Father, the moſt High God, and then takes upon him to prove that <hi>this Being</hi> is the moſt High God too. We will be ſo civil to him for once as to admit the firſt to be true; but the Holy Scriptures, and the reaſon of all Mankind will never ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſecond to be ſo too: for if they are not one, but two diſtinct individual Beings, they cannot both be the moſt High God. <hi>Yes,</hi> replies the Socinian Slain, <hi>that muſt be granted me too, as I will make it appear by twenty demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Arguments.</hi> Twenty Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions is a round number, but one good Demonſtration is as good as a thouſand; and I can produce a thouſand at any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98347:7"/>time of the day out of the <hi>1ſt</hi> and <hi>2d</hi> Book of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> as good and as concluſive as any of the 20 in the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Slain;</hi> but then I muſt expoſe my ſelf and the Holy Scripture too, as the <hi>Socinian Slain</hi> hath done; but God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid I ſhould be guilty of <hi>his Faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Socinian Slain,</hi> p. 3. tells you, <hi>The Holy Ghoſt made the Heavens and the Earth, and cites for a Proof</hi> Gen. 1.2. Who I pray is this Holy Ghoſt? a <hi>3d</hi> Divine Being, diſtinct in Number, Will, and Underſtanding, <hi>i. e.</hi> diſtinct in Perſon from the Father and the Son. If ſo, then we have three Creators, three Gods, three diſtinct Beings of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom and Power, which is two too many for Divine Revelation, and the moſt evident Reaſon of Mankind.</p>
            <p>No matter for that, the <hi>Socinian Slain</hi> will rather chooſe to have it ſo, than have his Arguments exploded as abſurd: And therefore on he goes, right or wrong, with his wonderful and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Proofs, and tells you in the next place, that, <hi>P.</hi> 4. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt is om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient, and therefore,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> 1ſt, <hi>He is ſo, becauſe he knows all the deep things of God; and</hi> 2ly, <hi>becauſe he knows all the deep things of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter of theſe two may be known without being omniſcient, and the former are known to God alone. Infinite Mind can only know what is in infinite Mind; but then that infinite Mind is but one.</p>
            <p>If he believes the Holy Ghoſt is one infinite Mind or Underſtanding diſtinct from another infinite Mind, and yet knows all that the other Infinite can comprehend then this Author's Faith is condemn'd by the Univerſal Church, the late <hi>Oxford</hi>-Decree, and by the Holy Scriptures: but if he believes God to be one infinite Mind and Being, who alone is conſcious to his own Thoughts, and no other Being beſides him is privy to 'em, as every Man knows his own Mind, and no other Man can know what's in his Mind till he reveal it to him, which is the true Senſe of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 10, 11. we are agreed, for undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly God knows all that he knows.</p>
            <p>The reſt of his Arguments are all of a piece, till you come to the 18th, unleſs you will except the eleventh, where he tells you, <hi>The Holy Ghoſt is the moſt High God, becauſe Sin and Blaſphemy againſt him are unpardonable;</hi> Now this ſeems the moſt concluding and deciſive Proof of all the 20 Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations; nay, as the Author manages it, it will prove more a great deal than ever he deſign'd it ſhould. For if the Holy Ghoſt be God becauſe Sin and Blaſphemy againſt him are unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; then the Father and Son can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo, becauſe all manner of Sins and Blaſphemies againſt them will be forgiven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.31. And now let this Writer conſider if he has not fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prov'd the Deity of the Holy Ghoſt, and excluded the other two Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from the moſt ſacred Order of his moſt high Gods. He has given the <hi>3d</hi> a greater Prerogative than the <hi>1ſt</hi> and <hi>2d</hi> Perſons, and ſo inſtead of prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him God equal to the Father and the Son, has prov'd him God ſuperiour in this reſpect to both: which is ſuch a way of proving he never had been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of, had he but conſulted his own Reaſon, or a good Commentator; and if he did it knowingly, 'tis very likely to be an unpardonable Sin.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Socinian Slain</hi> has but one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more that merits a Remark, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98347:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>that's his eighteenth. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſays he, P. 21. <hi>is one God with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son, and therefore is the moſt High God; I mean with reſpect to his Eſſence, ſince every Body will grant that the Father is ſo.</hi> What dos this Author mean by one God with the Father and Son? one Being with the Father and Son, or that the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are but one ſingle Being? If this be his meaning, tho it be not well expreſſed, yet it looks more like a Divine Unity, and is indeed the nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Trinity, and not the Tritheiſtic a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which I write. Or dos he mean by one God with the Father and Son, that the Holy Ghoſt is a God of the ſame Divine Kind with the Father and the Son? If this be his Senſe, as ſome other Paſſages ſeem to countenance, then without breach of Charity, I muſt charge him, tho I am ſorry for it, with down-right Tritheiſm or Polythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, which I take to be a much heavier Accuſation than any he can charge, or has fairly brought againſt his real Well-wiſhers the Unitarians.</p>
            <p>But the Author has another ambigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Phraſe in his Proof, and that is, <hi>That the Holy Ghoſt is moſt High God, with reſpect to his Eſſence.</hi> What, is he not ſo then with reſpect to his Perſon? if he be not ſo in Perſon, I don't ſee how he can be ſo at all; for what he is not as a Perſon, he is mot any other way; for all he is, is Perſon: <hi>No, no, the</hi> Socinian Slain <hi>can find out a way wherein he is the moſt High God, tho he be not ſo in Perſon.</hi> How I pray, not by Proxy certainly? No, <hi>but in Eſſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would fain know of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Socinian Slain</hi> what Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſignifies in this place, and in other Paſſages of his Book, for he ſeems to uſe it in no certain Senſe: which is unfair.</p>
            <p>The Schoolmen have us'd a Term in their Metaphyſical Writings:
<list>
                  <item>1. For common Nature, or kind of Being.</item>
                  <item>2. For particular Nature, or ſingle Being. And</item>
                  <item>3. For eſſential Properties of Being.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Will this Author be underſtood in any or none of theſe Senſes? If he mean by Eſſence, common Nature, or kind of Being; then Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, are three individual Gods numerically diſtinct in their Beings, but of the ſame ſort or Species of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature: this I think bids faireſt for his Senſe.</p>
            <p>Or dos he mean by Eſſence, ſingle Being? then Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are but three Names for one ſingle Almighty Being, and the proper Notion of Perſons in the Godhead will be loſt in this Senſe: yet this ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times muſt be his meaning, or what he ſays can have no meaning. And I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he does net underſtand the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt to be three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of one Deity.</p>
            <p>But let the Author, or any one for him, once aſcertain the Senſe of this term [Eſſence] and the Controverſy will ſoon determine it ſelf: but he and his Authors too, are unwilling to be plain in this matter, leſt the <hi>Myſtery</hi> vaniſhes, and <hi>Truth</hi> ſhould <hi>ſtare 'em in the Face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet after all, methinks the Author of the <hi>Socinian Slain,</hi> has in ſome Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges expounded his meaning, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly owns a <hi>plurality of Gods;</hi> and if the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98347:8"/>Reader conſiders what he ſays, and how he ſpeaks in ſome places, he will ſee there is no Reaſon to doubt of it.</p>
            <p>I will grant that he ſometimes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets himſelf, and ſpeaks of Almighty God as one ſingle Being: but his whole Book will correct that meaning; for he contends throughout, that religious Worſhip and Adoration are equally due, and to be paid to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and in all places ſpeaks of theſe three as three diſtinct individual Beings. For inſtance, in his 30th page he ſtiles the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Intelligent Almighty Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Operation, who created the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Page 31, 32, 33, 36. theſe three are ſpoken of as ſo many diſtinct Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in as plain terms as the Wit of Man can expreſs it; and how wary ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other Writers have been, the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian Slain</hi> will not and cannot but be underſtood in every Page of his Book diſcourſing of the Holy Ghoſt, as a real, proper, and abſolute Perſon in the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, really and intirely diſtinct from the Perſons of the Father, and the Son, in as true and proper a ſenſe as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Peter</hi> is complete in it ſelf, and numerically diſtinguiſh'd from the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> And if you would know of him how theſe three intelligent Beings, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are one; he frequently inculcates this Anſwer, <hi>That they are one in Eſſence, and one in Nature,</hi> or of one Divine Eſſence, and of one Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: which is juſt the ſame reply that every Body makes to this Queſtion, In what ſenſe may <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John, three diſtinct intelligent Beings,</hi> be ſaid to be one? Why the Anſwer is, They are one in Eſſence, or they are one in Nature; or they are of one human Eſſence, and of one human Nature. Now 'tis plain that Divine Eſſence and Nature, as well as human Eſſence and Nature, are abſtract Terms in ſuch Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages as theſe, and ſignify common Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or ſort of Being, comprehending divers particulars, or ſeveral Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als under it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Soc. Slain</hi> therefore, and all his Party are for a Specific Trinity of three Formal, Individual, Intelligent, Almighty Beings or Principles, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd under one common Nature, or of one divine ſort or kind of Being. And can any thing be more <hi>formal and palpable Tritheiſm</hi> than this? He diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes for a numerical Diſtinction of theſe three, and aſſerts only a ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Unity: nay, he aſſerts the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of theſe three Almighty Beings, and maintains an equal Right that all the <hi>Divine Three,</hi> or the <hi>three coequal Gods</hi> have to our religious Worſhip and Adoration, <hi>p.</hi> 19, 30, 36. <hi>ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> And when this is the Senſe and Language of all his Book, can he with any reaſon take it unkindly if he be underſtood to teach and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Doctrine of <hi>three Almighty Gods?</hi> In ſhort, if that be not his Senſe, all he writes and ſays muſt be Nonſenſe, how orthodox ſoever it may be thought by his Favourers. And whatever may be the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of ſome Mens Doctrines <hi>unfairly repreſented, P.</hi> 53. and the <hi>Tendency</hi> of ſome Mens Opinions <hi>untruly and diſingenuouſly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted:</hi> 'tis as evident as any thing can be, that this Writer's Doctrines and Opinions are in themſelves, and in their own nature, Heretical, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98347:8"/>Polytheiſtical, and Baſphemous.</p>
            <p>The Unitarians are charg'd without Reaſon, and without Scripture by their Adverſaries, with teaching Doctrines that lead to Infidelity and Atheiſm: Would to God this deteſtable Charge were no more true, when brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Socinian Slain</hi> and his Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtic Brethren! But whilſt they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to hold and profeſs that there are <hi>three infinite Minds, three eternal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, three Almighty Creators, three diſtinct individual moſt perfect Beings, three coequal Divine Perſons or Deities, to whom they pay distinctly Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and religious Adoration, and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematize and perſecute to the death, when the State permits 'em, all others of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Opinion:</hi> They muſt excuſe all the thinking and conſiderate part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from embracing their Faith, and believing their Contradictions.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Tritheiſts</hi> muſt pardon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> who heartily love their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but deteſt their Errors, if they are compell'd to declare that <hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> or the Doctrine, Belief, and Worſhip of 3 <hi>infinite Beings, Minds, or Gods,</hi> with diſtinct and coequal Veneration, is no Scripture-Doctrine, no Scripture-Faith, no Scripture-worſhip; but a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible abuſe of the true Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a violation of the Law of Nature, a ſtumbling-block to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometans,</hi> and a revival of Polytheiſm, or a plurality of Gods.</p>
            <p>And 'tis in vain for the moſt learned Tritheiſts, and much more vain for theſe illiterate Tritheiſts, to ſet about the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futing us, with one Book and Pamphlet after another. We know what they can ſay, and what they dare not ſay: We ſee what they drive at, and gueſs at their Deſigns; but till theſe equivocal Terms in their Books, <hi>viz.</hi> Nature, Eſſence, Perſon, Subſiſtence, Hypoſtaſis, and the like, are better explain'd, and ſet in their true light, we defy our <hi>Tritheiſtic Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries,</hi> with all their craft and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty, to purge themſelves and their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings from <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> and <hi>Equivocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And until they confeſs one infinite Mind, or intelligent Being, even the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to be the moſt High God, and that no other Being is to be compar'd, or equally ador'd with him <hi>(becauſe all other Beings are from Him, and he is from none; becauſe all other Beings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him have a Father, Cauſe, or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their Beings, and he has none; but by the Confeſſion of our Tritheistic Oppoſers, and all the Tritheistic Creeds, is the Fountain and Origin of all Beings)</hi> Until they will acknowledge this firſt of Beings to be the moſt High and Supreme God, or God in the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Senſe, and give Him peculiar Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Adoration as ſuch: We will tell 'em before-hand their Undertaking to confute us is deſperate, and our Principles are irrefutable: tho they ſhould write in <hi>defence of Tritheiſm</hi> as many Volumes in Folio as there are Stars in the Firmament, or Sands on the Sea-ſhoar, they will never be able to prove their <hi>Tritheiſm</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true or poſſible, as long as any Bibles remain in <hi>Christendom,</hi> or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon continues, in uſe among Men. But when our Reaſon has left us, and our Bibles are gone; they may decree and impoſe to good purpoſe, tho they can never diſpute with ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, there is not a ſingle Unitarian, but will heartily pity
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98347:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>miſtaken Tritheiſts,</hi> who have a Zeal, but not according to knowledg; and be always imitating the <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus</hi> in praying in the ſame manner, and to the ſame Object as he did, even <hi>to his Father and our Father, to his God and our God, that the thoughts of their hearts may be forgiven 'em,</hi> Joh. 20.17. that they may know the <hi>Father to be the only true God,</hi> and glorify <hi>him,</hi> chap. 17.3. even as <hi>Chriſt himſelf glorify'd him,</hi> chap. 17.4. that they may be ſanctified thro the Truth, and <hi>like true Worſhipers worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> as Chriſt himſelf did, Joh. 14.16. <hi>For the Father ſeeketh ſuch to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, who bow their Knees to the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, unto whom be glory in the Church by Jeſus Chriſt throughout all Ages, world without end.</hi> Amen. Eph. 3.14-21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the God of patience and conſolation grant, Rom.</hi> 15.5, 6. that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> and their miſtaken Brethren the <hi>Tritheiſts,</hi> may be of one Faith, <hi>likeminded one towards another, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Jeſus Chriſt; that we may with one mind and one mouth glorify God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And let all the People ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, have I given you ſome general Remarks upon theſe two new Writers, and their ſucceſsleſs Performances: and tho my leiſure will not admit me, and the merits of the Authors do not require me to make a diſtinct reply to every particular Text they pervert; yet I'm ſatisfy'd theſe few Obſervations and Replys I have made, are ſufficient to obviate the Scruples they have rais'd in the Minds of a few unwary Chriſtians. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>With great Veneration, Y. v. h. S-t, <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Oxford-<hi>Decree Engliſh'd.</hi> At a Meeting of Mr. Vice-Chancellor, and the Heads of Colleges and Halls in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Oxford, Novemb. 25. 1695.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>UPON occaſion of a Sermon lately preached before the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s in the Eaſt, on the Feaſt of St <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> laſt paſt, theſe words amongſt others were publickly ſpoken and aſſerted, <hi>viz. [There are three infinite diſtinct Minds and Subſtances in the Trinity]</hi> Item, <hi>[That the three Perſons in the Trinity are three diſtinct infinite Minds or Spirits, and three individual Subſtances,]</hi> which words gave many Perſons juſt cauſe of Offence and Scandal.</p>
            <p>Mr. Vice-Chancellor, and the Heads of the Colleges and Halls being now met together, in their General Meeting, judg, declare, and decree, That the foreſaid Words are falſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, and heretical; diſagreeing and contrary to the Doctrine of the Catholick Church, and ſpecially to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> publickly received.</p>
            <p>Wherefore they order and ſtrictly enjoin all and ſeveral the Perſons committed to their Truſt and Care, that for the future they do not maintain any ſuch Doctrine in their Sermons, or elſewhere.</p>
            <p>By the Decree of Mr. Vice-Chancellor and the Heads.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Ben. Cooper,</hi> Notary Publick, and Regiſter to the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>There was added in the <hi>London</hi> Account this Poſtſcript, <hi>viz.</hi> [<hi>It may be noted, that the Propoſitions above-mentioned, are Dr.</hi> S —k's, <hi>in his Diſcourſe of the Trinity, and the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of it; and wrote againſt by the Animadverter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
